Finding Aid for the Robert M. Emerson Papers LSC.2211
UCLA Library Special Collections
Robert M. Emerson papers
1964-1995
UCLA Library Special Collections
LSC.2211
4.4 linear feet (5 document boxes, 2 half size document boxes and 2 record cartons.)
Professor Emeritus Robert M. Emerson has worked for the Department of Sociology at UCLA for 45 years as a leader who was instrumental in building ethnomethodology as a field of inquiry. The collection consists of field notes, subject interview transcripts, academic papers, correspondence, grant proposals, reports and audiovisual recordings of his research projects concerning juvenile court and delinquency labeling, "The Pro Se Litigant: Self-Representation in Consequential Civil Cases," and "Resisting Imposed Relationships" which is also referred to as the Domestic Violence Project (DVP).
Restrictions on Access
COLLECTION STORED OFF-SITE AT SRLF: Open for research. Advance notice required for access. Contact the UCLA Library Special Collections Reference Desk for paging information.
PORTIONS OF THIS COLLECTION ARE RESTRICTED: Sensitive patient information (or PHI) and/or information and data covered under the Common Rule requires an approved Institutional Review Board (IRB) research protocol.
Portions of this collection are closed until 75 years after the listed dates: Box 2 folder 1 (1966), Box 3-4 (1966), Box 5 folders 4-5, 7, 11(1988), Box 6 folders 3-11(1988) and Box 8 folders 5-51 (1989).
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
COLLECTION CONTAINS AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: Audiovisual materials in this collection will require assessment and possible digitization for safe access. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Robert Emerson, 2008.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9973499483606533
Biography/History
Robert M. Emerson is UCLA Department of Sociology Professor Emeritus. Emerson graduated magna cum laude from Harvard's History Department in 1962 and received his M.A. and Ph.D. in Sociology from Brandeis University in 1964 and 1968. His dissertation is entitled The Juvenile Court: Labeling and Institutional Careers. Emerson began his career at UCLA in 1969 as Assistant Professor in the Department of Sociology, served as Vice Chair and Director of Graduate Studies from 1989-1992, and as Department Chair from 1995-1999. At the conclusion of his chairmanship, he worked as Faculty Director for UCLA's Center for Experiential Education and Service Learning (CEESL) from 2000-2001. Building on the foundational work of UCLA Sociology Professor Harold Garfinkel, Emerson was instrumental in the Department's development of ethnomethodology as a field of inquiry. Emerson is a committed ethnographer and prolific writer who authored numerous publications with fellow ethnomethodologist, UCLA Sociology Professor Melvin Pollner. Emerson's professional activities include work for the Editorial and Publications Committee of the Society for the Study of Social Problems, committee work for the American Sociological Association and editorial service for the following publications: Californian Sociologist, Journal of Contemporary Ethnography, Qualitative Sociology, Social Problems,Symbolic Interaction, Urban Life and Ethnography. Emerson describes his research as using qualitative field methods to examine both the indigenous dynamics of troubles, as in domestic violence situations, stalking and neighbor disputes, and formal, institutional responses to these troubles, particularly by the criminal justice and mental health systems.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of field notes, subject interview transcripts, academic papers, correspondence, grant proposals, reports and audiovisual recordings of his research projects concerning juvenile court and delinquency labeling, "The Pro Se Litigant: Self-Representation in Consequential Civil Cases," and "Resisting Imposed Relationships" which is also referred to as the Domestic Violence Project (DVP).
Organization and Arrangement
This collection has been arranged in the following series:
Series 1: Juvenile court research files.
Series 2: Pro se litigant research files.
Subseries 2.1: Domestic violence research files.
Series 3: Audio visual materials.
- Juvenile court research files., 1964-1968.
  Scope and Content
  Emerson's research files concerning his institutional analysis of a Boston juvenile court and the societal reaction approach to deviance with an emphasis on the labeling process in the court's handling of delinquency. Materials include papers, proposals, historical writings, field notes, lists of offenses and frequencies, probation officer personnel sheets, his signed dissertation, and guidelines and recommended practices for police and probation procedures in juvenile cases.
  Box 2, Folder 1: Restricted access and use because of probation officer names and personally identifiable information. This material is closed for 75 years from 1966.
  Box 3-4: Restricted access and use because of "juvenile offender" names and personally identifiable information. This material is closed for 75 years from 1966.
  - Juvenile court - early papers and proposals. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Cases - excerpts. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Thesis - cases, outlines. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Boston Juvenile Court - historical writings. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Documents, historical and personnel materials - BJC. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Restricted access and use because of probation officer names and personally identifiable information. This material is closed for 75 years from 1966.
  - Field notes - psychiatric evaluations of juveniles. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - The Juvenile Court: Labeling and Institutional Careers. (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Scope and Contents
    Emerson's bound, signed copy of his dissertation.
  - Field notes. (Box 4, Folder 1, Box 3)
    Restricted access and use because of "juvenile offender" names and personally identifiable information. This material is closed for 75 years from 1966.
  - Guides to fieldnotes - BJC. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Juvenile court clerk roll sheets. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Boston Juvenile Court miscellaneous writings. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Juvenile court revisions. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Court related agencies. (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Pro se litigant research files., 1988-1991.
  Files regarding Emerson and Dr. Susan M. McCoin's National Science Foundation (NSF) research grant funded project entitled, "The Pro Se Litigant: Self-Representation in Consequential Civil Cases." Materials include correspondence, grant proposals and evaluations, interviews with judges, Temporary Restraining Order (TRO) forms, Instructions for Lawsuits to Prohibit Harassment, Domestic Violence Project TRO forms and instructions, clippings and field notes. The acronym SMSC refers to Santa Monica Superior Court.
  Box 5, folders 4-5, 7, 11 and Box 6, folders 3-11: Restricted access and use because of litigant/subject names and personally identifiable information. This material is closed for 75 years from 1988.
  - Pro per - correspondence with judges. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - NSF - final report. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Pro per grant - correspondence, official papers, evaluations. (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Pro se grant - budget and administrative. (Box 5, Folder 4)
    Restricted access and use because personally identifiable information. This material is closed for 75 years from 1988.
  - Pro se/pro per - proposal copies. (Box 5, Folder 5)
    Restricted access and use because of personally identifiable information. This material is closed for 75 years from 1988.
  - Pro per - interviews with LA judges. (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Pro per - field notes and interviews. (Box 5, Folder 7)
    Restricted access and use because of litigant/subject names and personally identifiable information. This material is closed for 75 years from 1988.
  - Pro per notes - SMSC. (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Clippings - pro per SMSC. (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Pro per study interviews with SMSC officials (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - SMSC/pro per. (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Pro per court papers and forms. (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - TRO instructions. (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Pro pers SMSC field notes., 1989 Feb. (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Pro pers SMSC field notes., 1989 Mar. (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Field notes SMSC - Dept. J., 1989 April (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Pro per SMSC field notes., 1989 May (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Notes - Dept. J., 1989 Jun.-1989 Aug. (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Notes - Dept. J., 1989 Oct. (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Pro per interview guides. (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Pro per trials. (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Interviewee information. (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Domestic violence/law - lit. (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Restraining orders - lit. (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Claims-making lit. (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Self-representation - lit. (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Yvette Guerra. (Box 7, Folder 5)
    A copy of Guerra's paper, "Court Processing of Temporary Restraining Order Petitions" which includes Emerson's annotations and suggestions for revisions.
  - Pro per - Garot ms/paper. (Box 7, Folder 6)
    A copy of Robert Garot's paper, "The Separate Worlds of the Courthouse Workgroup and Litigants" which includes Emerson's annotations.
  - Pro per/TRO - writings and abstracts. (Box 7, Folder 7)
    Abstracts, manuscripts, conference papers and working papers by Emerson and Susan McCoin and NSF proposal evaluation forms.
  - Domestic violence project research files., 1989-1995
    These research files concern Emerson's "Resisting Imposed Relationships" research project which focused on women who have had an unwanted romantic relationship imposed upon them by means of harassment and violence. The proposal grew directly out of Emerson and Susan McCoin's NSF research project, "Self Representation in Consequential Civil Cases." The "Resisting Imposed Relationships" project was also referred to as the Domestic Violence Project (DVP) and focused on the problems people confront in completing applications for domestic violence temporary restraining orders (TROs) and was concerned with the help and support provided by family members, relatives, friends and others, in the decision to seek such restraining orders. The DVP project was funded in 1992 by the UCLA Center for the Study of Women (CSW) mini-grant program established in 1984 to assist faculty with pilot research projects that would ultimately lead to the development of a research proposal for extramural funding. Materials include CSW correspondence and grant application, notes for papers, correspondence with and application to UCLA Human Subject Protection Committee, Torrance domestic violence forms, Torrance Domestic Violence Clinic interviews, Domestic Violence Prevention Act face sheets, TRO coding sheets and field notes.
    Box 8, folders 5-51: Restricted access and use because of litigant/subject names and personally identifiable information. This material is closed for 75 years from 1989.
    - CSW Resisting Imposed Rels Grant, 1991-1992 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Human subjects DVRO, 1994-1995 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - DVC Torrance (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Field notes Ronna Stown DVP (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Field notes Ronna Stown DVP (Box 8, Folder 5)
      Restricted access and use because of litigant/subject names and personally identifiable information. This material is closed for 75 years from 1989.
    - Intake data DVP (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Eligibility/Screening DVP (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - DVP demographics (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Domestic Violence Project field notes (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - DVP 1 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - DVP 2 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - DVP 3 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - DVP 4 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - DVP 5 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - DVP 6 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - DVP 7 (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - DVP 8 (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - DVP 9A (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - DVP 9B (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - DVP 10 (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - DVP 12 (Box 8, Folder 21)
    - DVP 13 (Box 8, Folder 22)
    - DVP 14 (Box 8, Folder 23)
    - DVP 15 (Box 8, Folder 24)
    - DVP 16 (Box 8, Folder 25)
    - DVP 18A (Box 8, Folder 26)
    - DVP 18B (Box 8, Folder 27)
    - DVP 18C (Box 8, Folder 28)
    - Domestic Violence Project 19 (Box 8, Folder 29)
    - DVP 20 (Box 8, Folder 30)
    - DVP 21 (Box 8, Folder 31)
    - DVP 22 (Box 8, Folder 32)
    - DVP 23 (Box 8, Folder 33)
    - DVP 24 (Box 8, Folder 34)
    - DVP 25 (Box 8, Folder 35)
    - DVP 26 (Box 8, Folder 36)
    - DVP 27 (Box 8, Folder 37)
    - DVP 28 (Box 8, Folder 38)
    - DVP 30 (Box 8, Folder 39)
    - DVP 31 (Box 8, Folder 40)
    - DVP 32 (Box 8, Folder 41)
    - DVP 33 (Box 8, Folder 42)
    - DVP 34 (Box 8, Folder 43)
    - DVP 36 (Box 8, Folder 44)
    - DVP 37 (Box 8, Folder 45)
    - DVP 38 (Box 8, Folder 46)
    - DVP 39 (Box 8, Folder 47)
    - DVP 40 (Box 8, Folder 48)
    - DVP 41 (Box 8, Folder 49)
    - Civil harassment records, 1989 (Box 8, Folder 50)
    - Dom Vio records, 1989 (Box 8, Folder 51)
- Audio visual materials.
  Materials include audio recordings of field notes, interviews with research project participants and video recordings concerning topics such as kleptomania, multiple personality disorder and troubled kids.
  - Audio cassette tapes. (Box 9, Folder 1-70)
    Seventy audio cassette tapes.
  - Open reel audio tapes. (Box 9, Folder 71-76)
    Six open reel audio tapes.
  - Video cassette tapes. (Box 9, Folder 77-79)
    Three video cassette tapes.